So let us move on to a situation where I do
not have access to the MDP I am interested
in solving a problem but I do not have access
to the MTP and this is the most cases right
remember I motivated you about cycling pretty
with this whole thing about cycling and what
is your PS’ Sa in cycling all if you know
what the states are what the actions are you
might not be able to enumerate it but you
can kind of an intuitive feeling about what
the states and actions are.
But you cannot even begin to think of writing
down your PS’ given S, A right so maybe
you can some rough idea of what the expected
reward is right so if you fall down your bleeding
and things like that so negative reward and
those kinds of things but the transition for
dynamic sare hard to write but you still want
to solve this problems right.
.
So I want to look at the whole definition
of V?(S) All over again, so what is V?(S)
right? Such that is where we started off right
and then we wrote GTS GT+ ? may have an RT
+ ? GT + 1 and so on so forth which are there
simplifying but if I had not told you anything
else about this whole MDP business right and
if I told you that this is a random variable
GT is a random variable right and V?is the
expectation of the random variable and I asked
you to give me a way of estimating this expectation.
How will you do that, some random variable
I want to find the expectation of the random
variable sample and a lot of times and take
the average right that is the most straightforward
way of solving this right so what we mean
by saying sample GT a lot of times for other
policy ? so starts in some state S follow
policy ? until you come to some end and then
what you do you add up all the in some of
this some of the reward or some of the discount
is the word whatever you do.
Whether you use a ? or not in fact his here
I am not even telling you what the reward
is neither the ? is there or not is itself
a good thing so sum up everything that will
give me one sample right then what I do is
shattered S again that gives me the second
sample so like this I draw many samples by
executing ? multiple times and then I take
the average that gives me the value in sC
test.
He said all I can do with this trajectory
so from S I have gone to S1 right so can we
use this summation as a sample for V(S1) why
is that fine policy same and we had also assuming
things are Markov so it does not matter whether
it came from S2, S1 or for s’ to S1 let
him at all it matters is I started in this
one and from there on what I did right so
since I am assuming things are all markup
so I can do this.
So once what essentially what I should do
is you should generate a trajectory first
look at all the states that occur in the trajectory
and then after that take the sum of the rewards
that I get and you set as a sample so what
I do is a fix a policy ? and I am NOT going
to write down the pseudo code for this please
look it up in the book I am going to fix a
policy ? generate multiple trajectories, okay.
And use that to evaluate the policy so I could
get a P’ right so we call these kinds of
techniques as
Monte Carlo methods right because we are in
some sense using some form of a simulation
to get these samples right so I have this
model and they run trajectories on that I
get these samples and use that to update the
value function so these are called Monte Carlo
methods right and so this is a Monte Carlo
method for policy evaluation right sided policy
evaluation.
So what are the things that you have to note
here first thing is I do not really need the
model I do not really need the model I do
not really need the you are all I need is
a ways sampling from that system right I need
to be able to run trajectories according to
? okay. I really need to be able to run trajectories
coordinates all I need is a cycle and again
it is getting on the cycle and start pedaling
around and fall over fall down get hurt and
things like this all I need is a cycle.
I do not really need you to explain to me
what this PS’ Sa right so or if you want
to think of it in the herd management case
all you really need is a infinite supply of
course okay you start breeding them you see
what happens to them and then you know that
you can solve it right so some kind of gruesome
but you could you could do that is that is
essentially what we are talking about here
okay.
But you could also get by without the real
system right I do not give you an infinite
supply of cows or something but I give you
a simulation model so what I mean by a simulation
model let us give you an example so how many
of you have written programs to play games
anybody like play card games okay something
if you know about the game blackjack is an
example given in the book.
How many of you have heard of the name game
blackjack, really heard, heard only I am not
going to ask you to play here today okay,
so it is like how many of you saw the movie
what 21 yeah everyone says then you have a
blackjack now they are more confidents of
putting your hands up when they said how many
of you seen the movie21 do not worry I am
not going to play the movie here either.
So it is a card game where you deal a hand
of cards to people right and then people can
start turning over their cards and then they
have to make sure they get as close as two
21 as possible right so the state space would
be what, what cards you see right what cause
has your opponent has right, so you know the
first two cards then you know your cards and
then you can keep going if you want or stop
right.
Do you see your opponent cards you do not
have to stop before you see your opponent's
cards yeah you know to stop before I see up
front all right so you do not see opponent
card so you see whatever cards you have in
the keep going and what are their actions
yeah was it flush no I am not going to it
I am talking about 21blackjack so essentially
it is hit me or stay right again it is state
means you do not do this I hit me it give
me a more card right.
So that is all the two actions either continue
or stop right so that is basically it is a
very simple problem right but no if you want
to think of it as okay what is the probability
that the next card that flipped will be an
ace what is the probability the next car they
flip will be a king right then it becomes
a little tricky and it is right so it is you
have to do this on a specific game right and
then what is the probability that the opponent
will win given that these are the cars I have
turned over.
Now we have to come into your comment Oriole
summation all right what are many different
combinations that the operand can flip over
and that will actually be controlled by what
cards you have already flipped over all right
so this becomes a little tricky on the other
hand suppose I asked you to write a computer
program that will play 21 with me or blackjack
with me it is a fairly straightforward thing
right.
You just need to keep track of which cards
you have dealt and then randomly sample from
the other cards and then give it I do not
I can write the program that will play blackjack
with me much easily write much more easily
than actually writing a program that will
compute that PS’ S, A blackjack right, so
such models are called simulation models or
sample models okay this is already generate
samples.
But they are not a full specification of the
transition probabilities right, so I can run
these Monte Carlo methods with a sample model
I do not have to use the sample model to compute
my transition probabilities I can just leave
the sample one I can run Monte Carlo method
to the sample mall so that is one of the nice
things about Monte Carlo methods right, one
thing which I want you to note here is the
samples I draw like the trajectories are run
here.
Not only pick the states at which I will be
doing the evaluation they also give me the
value with which I will be doing the evaluation
right this expectation rate so whatever the
expectation computation that is also determined
by the sample later right so here when we
draw when we did trajectories you are only
using them for picking the states but the
updation was using this kind of a recursive
evaluation right using the model.
But here the trajectory is I draw not only
give me the state but they also give me the
rewards with which I am updating the value
of the state okay good, so this is called
Monte Carlo policy evaluation is there any
other question that you want to ask me here
and the ? could be stochastic why it should
be I am evaluating a ? and I am only interested
in evaluating a ? why it should be if ? is
deterministic you need to do one small additional
thing what is that.
Very simple I am talking about very practical
things here yeah I
have a fixed ? okay and look for the back
of a policy evaluation I have a fixed ? there
is no greedy no nothing business okay no exploration
business if I explore the policy will change
right I am giving you a fixed ? if I am going
to explore then that if the ? is probabilistic
then already and doing some kind of explains
to Casting I am doing some kind of exploration.
If the ? is deterministic if you know if we
explore on the ? then it is not no longer
? right I will come to that case later but
this is a good point now so what should I
do, I am interested in finding v ? (S) right
if I am only interested in the small subset
then a sufficient for me to start my trajectory
is only from that small subset but if I am
interested in finding the value for all these
TX in the MDP then I allowed to make sure
that I atleast start from each and every state.
Because it is a deterministic policy right
I have no guarantee that the states should
be visiting only a specific trajectory that
I will be following repeatedly right there
is no guarantee that the states that I do
not start from will ever be visited for me
to get samples from them so I have to start
from many different states so that I can get
samples from those states okay, so infact
even if it is a stochastic policy you will
have to do this exploring starts.
Because there is no guarantee that you will
hit every state even with the stochastic policy,
right unless the policy happens to be something
that log you to explore the entire state spaces
like a random policy if you have like a completely
random policy every state I pick an action
with probability half or whatever 1/n, so
I have n actions in each state like each action
with probability 1 by n.
That essentially means I leveled up covering
the entire state space provided no provided
the entire state space is reachable so I can
I can have a grid word like this that is a
wall right so everything here is I can go
everything here they can go if I start from
here and go even if I am acting randomly there
is no way I will go to this part of the world,
right if I start from here even if I am acting
completely randomly is no way I will go to
this part of the world right.
So they have not reachable from one another
was it how do you find do you need to is a
question so if you need to there are ways
of doing it for smaller problems for larger
and larger problems they become not ready
tractable right so you can use techniques
from dynamical systems you can use techniques
from physics you can use techniques from graph
theory depending on what assistance is set
up that you are interested in solving right.
So where were we so sample models then exploring
starts so is one other question that I am
expecting people to ask me no one is happening
you know I start from s I run a trajectory
so use the trajectory value for updating the
value of s, okay so what you hear sub KS again
in the physically this is two trajectory starting
from s or one trajectory sorry promise why
is it one when we started from S.
I said this is next state after case 1 then
we can consider that as a trajectory starting
from s 1 right and we are talking about probability
of transition is that even if I am using a
deterministic policy as a probability of transition
right so I may come to s and then I may skip
and go out of s and extreme as possible I
mean here is a simple example so I have S
only one action from S I do that so twenty
percent of the times I am going to come to
S and then I am going to stop right.
So S stop SSS stop so that is also going to
be perfection it is possible, which is correct
one trajectory or two trajectories? One trajectory
how many of you say one trajectory, no my
question was how many of you say one trajectory
either put your hand up or down put your hand
up so many said one trajectory yeah only one
person is putting his hand up okay, how many
of you say two trajectories.
What about the rest a tragic releases zero
you have to have an opinion I am going to
start from 0 again so I am going to keep going
until everybody put their hand up 0 okay turns
out both are right one and two right, so when
you do one it is actually call first we set
Monte Carlo when you say to what is called
close, it can be better than that right, so
if you use the only the first occurrence of
the state is called first visit protocol know
if you use every occurrence of the state is
called every visit want to call.
So when you say you use the first occurrence
what does it mean so I take the return occurring
after that let the entire thing you set as
one sample for updating v ? of it when you
say every visit that means I take the return
after every occurrence oh right so the first
return will be this much right now the second
return will be using will be this much okay,
so what is the real problem here is that when
I do every visit Monte Carlo.
I have just taken one sample trajectory right
but I am using the sample trajectory twice
atleast part of the sample trajectory I am
using it twice okay why is that a problem
yeah so is that a problem so when I approximate
an expectation with samples I am assuming
that the samples were drawn according to the
distribution on which I am taking the expectation
right, so the distribution yield at me this
one sample once right that one trajectory
delayed it once.
But I am using it twice essentially I am changing
the distribution right so that is a pain problem
so I am not using the same distribution that
I am taking the expectation with respect to
but it turns out that all this adds is a little
bit more biased estimation people remember
bias-variance strain of it is not very important
to know if you do not remember bias-variance
trade or never heard of bias variance.
So it induces a little additional bias into
estimator but I turns out that in the limit
right if you do a lot a lot of samples in
this particular case it turns out both converge
to the same value function so it is right,
see I roll the dice and take a sample right
I mean so essentially I am for every step
I take I roll the dice first pick an action
according to my ? then I pick a next state
according to PS’SA and then I pick a reward
according to the expected reward so on so
forth, I so I do a lot of simulation.
So a specific trajectory is now appeared so
S, s1 s2 s3 s4 and then for each one of these
I get r1 r2 r3 r4 and I would up into actions
a1 a2 a3 a4 right but then how many times
this kind of a thing occur should be determined
by rolling the dice again and again rolling
my coins again whatever right tossing the
coins again and again but I did not do that
right I just generated this once sample once
and I kept saying okay.
So this part is one sample now this part is
another sample this part is another sample
so for one roll of the die and this taking
multiple subsections of it and then repeatedly
using it right, so if I had started from S
here and rerun the experiment and I might
not that this might not be the one that I
produced that I will actually produce something
else again alright so essentially that is
the pet sitter keeper that is why I am saying
you are changing the distribution to some
extent.
Was it should not hurt the same saying it
will eventually converge to the same thing
so if at all there was a thought about why
you should not do every visit that was the
reason or it affects its effects in some sense
but it is it just how do I put it let us say
that there is something here that happened
right that is very rare very that it occurred
once right it will probably occur once in
a million times if you are actually random
independently it occurred once on this trajectory
.
But you are going to count it twice once for
this is one saw that is right but if you had
drawn independent samples it will happen only
once every million through the fleece now
it is happening twice everybody into the cliffs
which is a significant change, in something
you double the probability of it is missing
so that is that ids why it is it could be
a problem using a very visit NC could be a
problem right.
So there any questions on this so far the
thing you have covered all the things I wanted
to do so Monte Carlo equal to sample models
exploding starts first was it revisit.